Muhammad Abdul Karim

Birmingham, UK B13 0BT - +447501634676 - mohammed.a.karim98@gmail.com - linkedin.com/mak

Personal Statement

As a self-motivated Networks and Cybersecurity graduate with 3 years of progressive experience in the IT industry, I possess comprehensive knowledge in designing, implementing, administering, and supporting Cisco technologies. I am actively seeking opportunities to apply my skills and knowledge to a dynamic organization and expand my horizons by gaining new experiences that will enhance my abilities and understanding of the field.

Education

BSc (Hons) Networks and Cyber Security - First Class Honours

2019 - 2022 University of Sunderland - Sunderland, UK

Programming (C#, Python, JavaScript, and Flutter). **Networking** (Design, Administration, Troubleshooting, Switches, Routers, VPN, GRE Tunnels, Wireless Communication and Microcontrollers, and Telephony PBX with Asterisk etc.). Hypervisor **Virtualization** Technology (VMware, VirtualBox), Docker Containerization, Forensic methodology and Forensic software (Encase). **Cybersecurity** (Cryptography, Mitigation Strategies etc.)

Team Project: Drug Safety mobile application for Durham Constabulary, Responsible for Design & Programming.

Dissertation Project: A critical investigation of cybersecurity threats that are aimed at small-to-medium enterprises. With a website application aimed to train users and showcase hacking demos.

Skills

Network infrastructure and Security (MPLS, OSPF, BGP, IPsec, SD-WAN etc), Linux Environment, Wireshark, Docker, Active Directory, Bash Scripts, Windows 7 & 10, Microsoft Office, Databases, SQL, MongoDB, Programming (C, C#, JavaScript, Python, Java), React JS w/ MERN Stack, ITSM concepts and principles, Interpersonal Skills, Critical Thinking.

Work History

Junior Programmer - Thrive Creative Media – Dubai, U.A.E - 2018 – 2019

Responsible for the frontend development of mobile and web applications, primarily using Flutter/JAVA. As a junior programmer in the company, my role included:

- Interacted with clients to gather project information, translating their ideas from non-technical descriptions to technical for team.
- Worked on wireframes and designs for applications.
- Maintain, update, and improving existing client websites and applications.
- Worked closely with other team members on the development team, from requirement gathering to performing testing.

IT Support / System Administrator - Future Man HR & IT Consultants – Dubai, U.A.E - 2016 – 2018

- Install, configure and test new computer systems, software and other peripheral equipment.
- Troubleshoot computer hardware, software, user account issues, and network related connectivity issues ensuring connectivity and availability of services.
- Provide on-site and remote support to internal staff during work hours and out of work hours.
- Monitor and maintain integrity of network, server deployment, and security.
- Worked with I.T head to configure switches and routers to setup office network.

Certifications

- CCNA: Introduction to Networks.
- CCNA: Switching, Routing & Wireless Essentials.
- CCNA: Enterprise Networking, Security, and Automation.
- TryHackMe: Introduction to Cyber Security.